A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - General Files, Series P FA325
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - General Files, Series P
1894-1961 1920-1939
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Spelman Fund
China Medical Board (U.S)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller family
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.)
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller Brothers Fund
Standard Oil Company
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
Rockefeller Foundation
Davison Fund
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Sealantic Fund, New York
International Education Board
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
FA325
57 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Material in the Rockefeller family collections which provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net worth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
The files in this series are divided into 13 sections, as follows:
American Red Cross, Aid for the Blind, Charities, Cleveland Projects, Homes, Immigration, Jewish Organizations, Negro Organizations, Prisons and Prisoners, Prohibition and Alcoholism, Settlements, Science and Lecture Groups, United Service Organization.
Scope and Contents note
The materials in this series represent the Rockefeller family's involvement over the course of more than half a century with mainstream charitable and philanthropic organizations. With certain important exceptions, these papers focus on maintenance organizations, i.e., groups handling the chronic problems of the handicapped, alcoholics, juvenile delinquents, orphans, the aged, and the diseased. For this reason, much of the correspondence and other material contained here is of a routine nature and constitutes what was once called the "citizenship" obligations of the Rockefeller family.
The interests of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. predominate in these files, in particular his interest in Prohibition from about 1910 until Repeal in 1933 and his personal and financial contributions to the success of USO during World War II. Much of John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s early interest in Temperance, Prohibition, and settlement work can also be traced in these papers. John D. Rockefeller 3rd, because of his conscious choice to pursue a career in Philanthropy, is also well represented, in particular through his involvement with the youth work of the Community Service Society. Other members of the family appear only occasionally and then in the form of minor contributions to a few organizations.
The most historically significant material contained in the Welfare General Interests series relates to the Prohibition and Temperance movements, the support for black organizations such as the National Urban League and the NAACP, and the pervasive pattern of support for urban reform manifested by office involvement with the settlement house movement in Cleveland and New York City.
Broader streams of change can also be traced through these files, particularly the centralization of philanthropic organization which the Rockefeller family both encouraged and supported. This trend can best be seen in the emergence of the Community Service Society, the Greater New York Fund, the Welfare Council of New York, and other efforts at federation and consolidation.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Economic development; Art; Religion; Public welfare; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Folk art; Urban policy; Urban renewal; Travel; United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Philanthropy -- United States; World War I; World War II; Performing arts; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Maternal health services; Medical care; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Medical education; Medical research; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Charities -- Investments; Charities; International relations; International education; International economic relations; International cooperation; Business; Arts; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Philanthropy; Public health administration; Public policy; Prohibition; Public health; Mauze, Abby Rockefeller; Spelman Fund; China Medical Board (U.S); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller family; Spelman family; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller, John D.; Rockefeller, David; Rockefeller Center; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Standard Oil Company; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison); Rockefeller Foundation; Davison Fund; Rockefeller, Winthrop; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman; Sealantic Fund, New York; International Education Board; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
- American Red Cross
  - American Red Cross - General, 1906-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Mabel T. Boardman's appeal for aid in 1906 declined. Appeals for various Red Cross activities, buildings, and endowment funds declined. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. joined as $1.00 member in 1916. Rockefeller Foundation grants; World War I activities. There is a gap in this file between 1927 and 1937. Nelson A. Rockefeller contributions for Haitian relief, 1954; information on International Red Cross. Correspondents include Mabel T. Boardman, Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Will Rogers, Herbert Hoover, Walter Gifford, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    File Plan note
    45
  - American Red Cross - Memorial Building, Washington, 1913-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Rockefeller Foundation gift towards site.
  - American Red Cross - Russian Red Cross, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Appeals declined.
  - American Red Cross - Flood Relief, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000 toward campaign.
  - American Red Cross - Membership Dues, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Red Cross - Clippings, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Red Cross - Westchester Chapter, 1916-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Family memberships, special contributions.
  - American Red Cross - China Relief, 1907-1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    China Family Relief Committee work; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Appeals to John D. Rockefeller, Sr. from Cleveland. Discussion of shipment of gasoline to Italy through Standard Oil of New Jersey. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Contributions - Rockefeller Foundation, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - Contributions, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Contributions raised by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - Foundation Pledge, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Discussion and payment of $5,000,000 by Foundation.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - Dividends Payable to John D. Rockefeller, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Endorsement of company dividends over to Red Cross.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - New York City Fund Committee, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. was a member, captain of soliciting team.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - Summary of Gifts, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and companies.
  - American Red Cross - War Fund Campaigns - Printed Material, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Red Cross - Relief of Stranded Americans, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Loan fund set up by Red Cross at State Department's request; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts. Correspondents include Arthur Woods, Kenneth Chorley, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, JR.
  - American Red Cross - Christmas Seals, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Annual contributions by John D. Rockefeller, 1908-1917. Large gifts totaling $40,000 by Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Fund and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; no later gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
    45.3
  - American Red Cross - Contributions, 1898-1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions toward special causes such as victims of Italian earthquakes or Mississippi floods, wounded in Spanish-American War, Armenian refugees, tornado victims, etc. Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller gifts to local chapters. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mabel T. Boardman.
  - American Red Cross - Contributions, 1930-1957 (Box 2, Folder 0019A)
  - American Red Cross - Contributions, 1941, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 0019B)
  - American Red Cross - Contributions - Pledge, May 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and family gave $100,000 for war relief.
  - American Red Cross - Contributions - Pledge, May 1940 (Box 2, Folder 0020A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Family contributions.
    45.1
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    45.2
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    45.4
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    45.5
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    45.6
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    45.7
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    45.8
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    45.9
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 0031A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    45.10
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    45.11
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 0034A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    45.12
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 0036A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    45.13
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 0038A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    45.14
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    45.15 and 45.16
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    45.17
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    45.18
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    45.19
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 0047A)
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    45.20
  - American Red Cross - Annual Campaign Contributions, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - American Red Cross - Clippings, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - American Red Cross - Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Aid for the Blind
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Association for the Blind, 1907-1960 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    Irregular contributions by John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Arthur W. Packard.
    75
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Association for the Blind - Vacation Fund, 1923-1931 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. annual contributions to fund.
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Association for the Blind - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1951-1961 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    One gift of $20,000 made in 1952. Other appeals declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Association for the Blind - David Rockefeller, 1940-1961 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    Annual contributions. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Association for the Blind - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1941-1961 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    Annual contributions by Mary French Rockefeller. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Mary F. Rockefeller.
  - Aid for the Blind - Blind Appeals - Miscellaneous, 1949-1961 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    Appeals for special projects and programs to aid the blind all declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    75.1
  - Aid for the Blind - Blind Appeals - Industrial Home for the Blind, 1924-1959 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made one gift, 1924. Later requests were declined.
  - Aid for the Blind - Blind Appeals - Recording for the Blind, 1954-1961 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for the Blind, 1926-1961 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    Some small gifts by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Helen Keller, Robert Irwin.
    75.2
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for the Blind - Helen Keller, 1927-1961 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s personal regard for Miss Keller. Gifts for special purposes. Use of Miss Keller's letter about Rockefeller Center for advertising purposes.
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for the Blind - Pledge, 1927, 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $100,000 toward general purposes of the Foundation.
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for the Blind - Pledge, 1929, 1929-1931 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $10,000 toward International Conference for workers for the Blind.
  - Aid for the Blind - The Seeing Eye, 1934-1961 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    Gifts by Margaret (Peggy) McGrath Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauz, Mary French Rockefeller, and declinations by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and sons. Correspondents include Margaret (Peggy) McGrath Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauz.
    75.3
    General note
    DR material removed to Folder 64A.
  - Aid for the Blind - The Seeing Eye, 1934-1961 (Box 6, Folder 0064A)
    Declinations by David Rockefeller.
  - Aid for the Blind - The Eye Bank for Sight Restoration, 1945-1961 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Contributions by Mary Todhunter Clark Rockefeller; other appeals declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Mary Clark Rockefeller.
    75.4
  - Aid for the Blind - New York Institute for the Education of the Blind, 1933-1961 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    All appeals were declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    75.6
  - Aid for the Blind - Associated Blind, Inc., 1941-1961 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    Appeals were declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    75.7
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for Overseas Blind, 1945-1959 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    David Rockefeller contribution, 1946; John D. Rockefeller 3rd gift, 1959; other appeals declined. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Helen Keller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Dana S. Creel.
    75.8
  - Aid for the Blind - American Foundation for Overseas Blind, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 0068A)
  - Aid for the Blind - John Milton Society for the Blind, 1948-1959 (Box 6, Folder 69)